JIVJOT SINGH

Ludhiana, Puniab

■ +91-6283-274892 | ■ 121jsingh@gmail.com | ☑ github.com/SinghJivjot | 🛅 linkedin.com/in/jivjot-singh16

PERSONAL PROFILE

An IISER Mohali Physics graduate student majoring in **Astrophysics** with a specialization in Data Science, transitioning to a career as **Machine Learning Researcher**. Passionate to expand the **one & a half year** experience with recent focus on developing Demand Forecasting & Generative AI solutions as a Research Assistant at IIIT Delhi.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant Oct 2023 - Present

Infosys Centre for AI, Indraprastha Institute of Information Technology, Delhi

Delhi, India

- Deploying LangChain built Generative AI applications on Streamlit to aid content generation for a shopping website
- Crafted nested chains by combining Open-source LLMs on Ollama with SEO tools, in-context memory buffers, vector stores etc. alongwith Zero-Shot & One-Shot Dynamic Prompting
- Automating scheduled pipelines on Azure ML Studio for Demand Forecasting & Inventory Management using AutoGluon Time Series & Nixtla libraries
- Trained **Entity Embeddings** in combination with **Tabular Clustering** to counter temporal data-sparsity & integrated filtering criteria to improve the forecast correlation

Research Intern Jun 2023 - Sep 2023

Institute of Data Sciences, Indian School of Business, Mohali

Mohali, India

• Worked on **Topic Modelling** of grievance data from Punjab Government to identify district-wise issues using **BERTopic**

Project Intern May 2023 - Jun 2023

Tatras Data Remote

• Worked on scraping images from Instagram using **Selenium** & classify real vs fake food influencers with **Fine-tuned ResNet50**

Data Science Intern

Jan 2023 - Jun 2023

Sabudh Foundation Remote

• Built a Medical Chatbot in RASA & excelled in Kaggle competitions - Frame Level Speech Recognition & Document Classification

PROJECTS

GitHub Repos Jan 2023 - Mar 2023

- Carried out Research Paper Implementations of different Generative Adversarial Networks in pure PyTorch Vanilla GAN, Deep Conv GAN vs Wasserstein with Gradient Penalty GAN, Conditional Pix2Pix GAN and Progressive GAN
- Implemented classic ML algorithms like, KNN, Linear & Polynomial Regression in pure NumPy
- Used Monte Carlo Approximation to visualize the value of pi

Speech Recognition Mar 2023 - Apr 2023

Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Mohali

Mohali, India

- Built **TensorFlow** routines for expanding temporal context & **Deep Residual-Conv** models to perform Phoneme Classification
- Combined Bi-LSTM & Conv2D layers to classify at an utterance level using Functional, Sequential & Sub-classing methods

Multi-Layer Perceptron using NumPy

Feb 2023 - Mar 2023

Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Mohali

Mohali, India

• Created an **Object-Oriented** code base that implements the complete architecture of **MLP from scratch**

IPL batting partnership Network Analysis

Sep 2022 - Oct 2022

Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Mohali

Mohali, India

Performed Web Crawling of ESPN to aggregate partnership statistics & built Network Graphs to rank key players

MASTERS THESIS

Dissertation: Multi-wavelength analysis of the NGC 3227 group using AstroSat

May 2022 - Apr 2023, 5 yrs

Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Mohali

Mohali, India

- · Designed code implementing an innovative approach for distinguishing faint astronomical objects
- Discovered a Tidal Dwarf Candidate, exclusively observable in the AstroSat image of galaxy NGC 3227
- Defended my thesis in front of the Astrophysics committee through Poster, PowerPoint & ETEX presentations

EDUCATION

Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Mohali

Aug 2018 - May 2023

BS-MS with Major in Physics & Minor in Data Science

Mohali, India

• **Relevant Courses:** Python Programming, Analysis in one variable, Probability & Statistics, Non-linear dynamics, Machine Learning, Data Science, Design & Analysis of Algorithms

Sacred Heart Senior Secondary School

Mar 2016 - Apr 2018

Ludhiana, India

High School
• **Subjects**: Physics, Chemistry, Maths, English & Fine Arts

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Python Libraries TensorFlow, PyTorch, Transformers, LangChain, NumPy, Matplotlib, Plotly, Pandas, Scikit-learn

Miscellaneous LTEX, Git, Linux, Microsoft Office, Quarto

Soft Skills Research, Adaptability, Time Management, Problem-solving, Documentation, Presentation